Louis-Alexandre Berthier Collection, 1780-1783: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
Louis-Alexandre Berthier Collection
1780-1783
C0022
Princeton University Library. Special Collections. Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
1 linear feet 14 custom portfolio cases 1 half-size archival box
Berthier, Louis-Alexandre, 1753-1815.
The collection consists primarily of a set of handcolored, topographical, manuscript maps (111 of them), created by Louis-Alexandre Berthier, an officer on General Rochambeau's staff, depicting the historic overland march of the French and American forces from Philipsburg, New York, to Yorktown, Virginia, in 1781 and their return march to Boston, Massachusetts, in 1782. Accompanying these maps is Berthier’s journal (in French), providing a detailed description and explanation of the routes covered by the maps. In addition, there are documents and memoranda concerning French military events in America, Berthier’s departure from France in 1780, and his return to France via the West Indies in 1782-1783.
Louis-Alexandre Berthier (1753-1815), one of the four sons of Jean-Baptiste Berthier, was born in Versailles, where his father was in charge of the Royal Map Service. He entered the army as a young man; in 1777, at the age of twenty-four, he attained the rank of captain. In 1780 he asked to be assigned to Rochambeau's army which was preparing to leave for America, and was offered a place on the staff of Count de Saint-Maisme who commanded the Soissonais regiment. Through a series of mishaps and misunderstandings (related in the journal in the Princeton Library), Berthier did not leave with Rochambeau's army when it sailed from Brest in May 1780, but proceeded to America via the West Indies and finally joined up with the army at Newport, Rhode Island, on September 30, 1780.
In January 1781, Captain Berthier was assigned to the staff of General Rochambeau, as "aide maréchal général des logis surnuméraire." In this capacity he accompanied the army in 1781 on its march to Yorktown, and in 1782 on its return march to Boston, and thence to the West Indies, before returning to France. In all, Berthier was in the United States from September 30, 1780, until December 24, 1782.
After his return to France, Berthier was sent on a military mission to Prussia in 1783. (The Journal of this mission is among the manuscripts at Princeton.) He continued to be employed in staff posts, and to earn regular promotions. When the French Revolution came he again saw active service in the field. In 1796 he accompanied General Bonaparte in the Italian campaign, as chief of staff of the army. Henceforth, his fortunes were linked to those of Bonaparte. Berthier participated in the coup d'état of the 18th Brumaire (1799) which established the Consulate, and received the post of Minister of War. Soon after Bonaparte became Emperor Napolean I, in 1804, he chose Berthier as one of the eighteen army officers to be named Marshal of the Empire. Subsequently, Berthier acquired other titles: Duke of Valangin, Price of Neufchâtel, Prince of Wagram. Marshal Berthier was with Napolean in the campaigns of Austerlitz, Jena, and Friedland; he was in the Peninsular Campaign (1808), the Austrian Campaign (1809), in Russia (1812), Germany (1813), and France (1814). In 1814 he abandoned Napoleon, and died the following year, on June 1, 1815, at Bamberg.
Berthier's maps, numbering 111, are the most notable feature of the collection. They do not comprise an atlas or a series of separate items, but, rather, they are the consecutive record of that important and historic Revolutionary War military event, the overland march of the French Army under Rochambeau (joined by American forces at Philipsburg) from Newport to Yorktown during the summer and early autumn of 1781, and the return march of the French Army from Virginia to Boston the following year, July - December 1782. These were executed, presumably soon after the event, from information and sketches made on the spot while Berthier was accompanying Rochambeau's Army in America. The maps fall into two interrelated series: the first showing the French Army's camp sites on the southward march from Newport, Rhode Island, to Yorktown, Virginia, in 1781, and on the return march northward in the summer and autumn of 1782; the second showing the "itineraries" or daily marches of the Army (from Newport as far as Elkton, Maryland, in 1781; the daily marches for the 1782 northward journey are lacking among the Princeton papers.) Another set of Berthier's maps is preserved among the Rochambeau Papers in the Library of Congress; this set, although duplicating in part the Princeton set, is apparently less complete
Although Berthier's maps are the most spectacular part of these papers at Princeton, they cannot be fully appreciated without the accompanying textual material of his journal (1780-1783), which provides a detailed description and explanation of the routes covered by the maps. In addition, there are related manuscripts and documents, including a letter (1785) from Rochambeau, notes on the history of Virginia, and Berthier's journal of his later visit to Prussia (1783).
The originals are restricted. Users are asked to use the online surrogates.
These manuscripts of Louis-Alexandre Berthier were presented to Princeton in 1939 by Harry C. Black, Class of 1909. They were purchased from Maggs Brothers, Ltd., of London, which had previously acquired them from family archives preserved by Berthier’s descendents at the Chateau de Grosbois in France.
More about the collection coming to Princeton can be found in Gilbert Chinard's article "The Berthier Manuscripts: New Records of the French Army in the American Revolution" in The Princeton University Library Chronicle, Volume I, No. 1 (November 1939), pp. 3-8.
No appraisal information is available.
This collection is also available in microfilm.
Berthier's journal and maps were translated and edited by Howard C. Rice, Jr., and Anne S. K. Brown in their two-volume work The American Campaigns of Rochambeau's Army 1780, 1781, 1782, 1783 (Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1972).
These papers are housed in the original red portfolio cases (and order) in which they were presented to the Library in 1939.
Rice and Brown cite several sources in their descriptions used in this finding aid:
Berthier's journal: "Journal of Louis-Alexandre Berthier," which is translated and edited by Rice/Brown in Volume 1 (pp. 189-282) of their 1972 work cited above
Chastellux: Travels in North America in the Years 1780, 1781 and 1782 by the Marquis de Chastellux (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1963), a revised translation with introduction by Howard C. Rice, Jr.
Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal: "Journal of Jean-François-Louis, Comte de Clermont-Crèvecœur," which is also translated and edited by Rice/Brown, Volume 1 (pp. 1-100) of their 1972 work cited above
Verger's journal: "Journal of Jan-Baptiste-Antoine de Verger," which is also translated and edited by Rice/Brown, Volume 1 (pp. 101-188)
Von Closen's journal: The Revolutionary Journal of Baron Ludwig Von Closen, 1780-1783 (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1958), translated and edited with an introduction by Evelyn M. Acomb
Rochambeau, Jean-Baptiste-Donatien de Vimeur, comte de, 1725-1807-- Military leadership; France. Armée--Officers--18th century--Notebooks, sketchbooks, etc.; Military topography--United States--18th century; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Participation, French; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Personal narratives, French; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Sources; United States--History, Military--18th century--Sources; Yorktown (Va.)--History--Siege, 1781--Sources; Journals (accounts)--18th century; Military maps--18th century; Topographic maps--18th century; American history/Colonial; Cartography
- Series 1: Berthier's Personal Journal, 1780-1783; 2 portfolios (1 partial)
  This is not, strictly speaking, a day-to-day diary, but rather a connected narrative, probably rewritten from rough notes, addressed to "a friend" in France. Berthier's personal journal, as it exists among these papers, does not cover the period from August 27, 1781, to December 22, 1782.
  The manuscripts are arranged chronologically in string or ribbon-tied packets that are numbered sequentially.
  The journal is described and translated in Howard C. Rice and Anne S. K. Brown, The American Campaigns of Rochambeau's Army (Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1972), Volume 1, pp. 189-282.
  - Lettre en journal a un de mes amis depuis mon départ de france ...., 1780 May 10 - 1781 March 8; 1 item 40 pp 32 x 21 cm 2 blank pages (Portfolio I, Packet 1)
    Journal: covers his departure from Brest, visit to the West Indies, arrival in Newport, and winter quarters in Rhode Island.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 1. [Rice/Brown, pp. 221-242]
  - [Continuation from No. 1], 1781 March 8 - 1781 August 26; 1 item 36 pp 32 x 21 cm 11 blank pages (Portfolio I, Packet 2)
    Journal: covers naval engagement of Destouches' squadron (16 March 1781), preparations for leaving Rhode Island, march across Connecticut to join American forces at Philipsburg near the Hudson, and departure of the combined armies for Yorktown, August 1781.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 2. [Rice/Brown, pp. 242-255]
  - Sea Campaigns, 1782 December 23 - 1783 March 14; 1 item 40 pp 32 x 21 cm 4 blank pages (Portfolio II, Packet 3)
    Journal: covers departure from Boston aboard Le Souverain, arrival at Curaçao, death of Berthier's younger brother (Charles-Louis-Jean Berthier), and journey to Caracas.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 3. [Rice/Brown, pp. 256-276]
  - Journey to Caracas (continued), 1783 March-1783 April; 1 item 28 pp 32 x 21 cm 17 blank pages (Portfolio II, Packet 4)
    Journal.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 4. [Rice/Brown, pp. 276-282]
  - Voyage à Caracas, 1783 March-April; 1 item 38 pp 31 x 20.5 cm 6 blank pages (Portfolio II, Packet 5)
    Second version of the first part of No. 4. Journal.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 5.
- Series 2: March of the French Army from Providence to Virginia, March 1781 - October 1781, 10 portfolios (1 partial)
  This series consists of maps, memoranda, and documents regarding French military events in America during months of 1781.
  The documents and maps are arranged chronologically by packet/item number that continue (for the most part) the numbering begun in the previous series.
  Descriptions for the maps have been taken verbatim from Howard C. Rice and Anne S. K. Brown, The American Campaigns of Rochambeau's Army (Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1972), Volume 2. Leading numbers in the map titles correspond to numbers assigned to the maps by Rice and Brown; these numbers are used in their descriptions to refer to other Berthier maps. (The actual Princeton/Berthier number for the map is provided at the end of each description.) Gaps in the Rice-Brown numbers reflect the fact that they also draw from other sources in their work (i.e., also describe other maps). Measurements, in centimeters, give the size of the sheets.
  - Journal de la Sortie de l'Escadre française commandée par Monsier le chevalier Destouches, appareillée le 8 Mars de la radde de Newport, et rentrée le 26 du même mois, 1781; 1 item 5 pp 23 x 19 cm (Portfolio III, Packet 6)
    Journal, including account of the naval engagement off Chesapeake Bay, March 16, 1781. (Berthier went on this expedition.)
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 6.
  - Relation de l'Escadre Française, aux ordres du Cher. Destouches, & de l'affaire qui a eue lieu le 16 Mars 1781, entre cette Escadre & celle des Anglais, commandée par l'Amiral Arbuthnot, dates not examined; 1 item 4 pp printed document (Portfolio EX1081.755)
    Account of the engagement of March 16, 1781, printed on the Press of the French Fleet, at Newport.
    Catalogued and housed in Rare Books under this call number.
    Cf. John Eliot Alden, Rhode Island Imprints no. 865.
  - Project pour porter l'armée de Providence à King's ferry à la rive gauche de la Rivière du Nord [Hudson River] en 17 jours de marche y compris trois Séjours, 1781; 1 item 24 pp 23 x 19 cm (Portfolio IV, Packet 8)
    Plan for Marching the Army from Providence to King's Ferry on the East Bank of the Hudson River in 17 Days, Including Three Stopovers. Memorandum giving instructions concerning the march of the French armies from Rhode Island to the Hudson River, June 1781.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 8. [Rice/Brown, pp. 7-17]
  - Etat des Différents Camps occupés par L'Armée française, 1781; 1 item 4 pp 35 x 23 cm Document. Last page blank. (Portfolio V, Packet 20)
    List of the French Army's Campsites (Nos. 1-40) from Providence, Rhode Island, to York, Virginia.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 20.
  - Itinéraire des Marches qu'a fait l'Armée Française pour se rendre de Providence au camp de Philip'sburg, 179 milles, 1781; 1 item 32 pp 33 x 21 cm route book (Portfolio V, Packet 9)
    Itinerary of the Marches of the French Army from Providence to the Camp at Philipsburg, 179 Miles.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 9. [Rice/Brown, pp. 19-36]
  - Itinéraire des Marches que L'Armée a fait pour se rendre du camp à Philipsburg au camp devant Yorck en Virginia en 1781. Premier Cahier - de Philipsburg à Wippany, 86 Milles ½, 1 item 28 pp 33 x 20 cm route book (Portfolio V, Packet 10)
    Itinerary of the Marches of the French Army from the Camp at Philipsburg to the Camp before York in Virginia in 1781. Part I: From Philipsburg to Whippany, 86½ Miles.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 10. [Rice/Brown, pp. 37-58]
  - Itinéraire des Marches que L'Armée a fait pour se rendre du camp à Philip'sburg au Camp devant Yorck. Deuxieme Cahier - de Wipany à Princetown, 44 Milles, 1781; 1 item 20 pp 33 x 20 cm Route book. Last 7 pages blank. (Portfolio V, Packet 11)
    Itinerary of the Marches of the French Army from the Camp at Philipsburg to the Camp before York in Virginia in 1781. Part II: From Whippany to Princeton, 44 Miles.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 11. [Rice/Brown, pp. 59-67]
  - Itinéraire des Marches que L'Armée a fait pour se rendre du camp à Philip'sburg au Camp devant Yorck. Troisieme Cahier - de Princetown à Head-of-Elk, 89 Milles ½, 1781; 1 item 20 pp 33 x 20.5 cm Route book. Last 4 pages blank. (Portfolio V, Packet 12)
    Itinerary of the Marches of the French Army from the Camp at Philipsburg to the Camp before York in Viriginia in 1781. Part III: From Princeton to Head of Elk, 89½ Miles.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 12. [Rice/Brown, pp. 69-81]
  - Itineraire des Marches faittes par les Equipages de L'Armée pour se rendre du Camp d'Anapolis à Williamsburg, 219 Milles, 1781; 1 item 32 pp Route book. Last 14 pages blank. (Portfolio VI, Packet 13)
    Itinerary of the Wagon Train of the Army from the Camp at Anapolis to Williamsburg, 219 Miles.
  - Figuré de la Route et des differents Camps que l'Armée Françoise a occupé depuis Providence jusqu'à la réunion des deux Armées au Camp de Philips-burg, undated; more than 13 packets 23 x 16 cm (dimensions of cahier when closed; the fold-out sheets are of varying width) (Portfolio VII, Packet 14)
    Figuration of the Route and of the Different Camps Occupied by the French Army from Providence to the Junction of the Two Armies at the Philipsburg Camp. This heading appears on the cover of the first of a series of "cahiers" containing the road maps of the army's march. Each sheet includes the route for one day's march, usually covered on four successive days by the four divisions. The point of departure is at the left, the destination at the right. The campsites are shown in more detail in another series of the maps, below, Nos. 26ff.... The "Itineraries," above, give a detailed description of the route and should be read as commentary on the road maps; further identification of localities is given in the notes to the "Itineraries."
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 14 (1-12). No other set of these road maps has been found. The wash in this cahier (our Nos. 14-25) is brownish yellow, but green in those following (our Nos. 48ff.). [Rice/Brown, pp. 128-129]
    See also the pertinent portions of Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal (pp. 28ff.) and of Berthier's journal (pp. 246ff).
    - 14. March en Amérique de l'Armée Française aux ordres de Mr. le Cte. de Rochambeau. Le 11 et le 12 Juin les deux brigades qui composent l'armée se sont embarquées pour se rendre à Providence et y ont occupé le Camp cy marqué. Premiére Journée. Le 18, 19, 20, 21. de Providence à Waterman's Tavern, 15 milles, undated; 1 item 23 x 29 cm (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-1)
      First Day's March: from Providence to Waterman's Tavern. 18-21 June 1781. This map shows the route taken by the four divisions, successively, on 18-21 June 1781. The composition of the divisions is explained in the "Plan for taking the Army from Providence to King's Ferry on the east bank of the Hudson River...," above, Itinerary I. "Among Town" is Monkey Town (Knightsville). The "Patasket" is the Pawtuxet River. Waterman's Tavern was in the town of Coventry, Rhode Island (near present Pottersville).
      MS, No. 14-1. The dimensions given here for the road maps are those of the sheet on which the original was drawn. [Rice/Brown, p. 129]
    - 15. Seconde Journée. Le 19, 20, 21, 22 de Waterman's Tavern à Plainfield, 15 milles, undated; 1 item 23 x 41.5 cm (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-2)
      Second Day's March: from Waterman's Tavern to Plainfield [in Connecticut]. 19-22 June 1781. The "Musclover" is the Moosup River. "Walen Town" is Voluntown (now Sterling Hill, Connecticut); "Dalens Taverne" is Dorance's Tavern. (The army camped here on its return march the following year, 8-9 November 1782; see No. 155, below.)
      MS, No. 14-2. [Rice/Brown, p. 129]
    - 16. Troisième Journée. Le 20, 21, 22, 23 de Plainfield a Windham, 15 milles, undated; 1 item 23 x 37.5 cm (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-3)
      Third Day's March: from Plainfield to Windham. 20-23 June 1781. The curious reversed lettering of "chemin de Boston," left of Windham on the map, is presumably a copyist's error, perhaps arising from some tracing device used when making a fair copy of the map.
      MS, No. 14-3. [Rice/Brown, p. 129]
    - 17. Quatrieme Journée. Le 21, 22, 23, 24 de Windham à Bolton, 16 milles, undated; 1 item 23 x 40 cm (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-4)
      Fourth Day's March: from Windham to Bolton: 21-24 June 1781. The "Rivière de Windham" is now called the Shetucket. The 4th camp was located in the town of Bolton, at the spot now known as Bolton Center.
      MS, No. 14-4. [Rice/Brown, p. 129]
    - 18. Cinquième Journée. Le 22, 23, 24, 25 de Bolton à East Hartford, 12 milles 1/2, undated; 1 item 23 x 33.5 cm (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-5)
      Fifth Day's March: from Bolton to East Hartford. The four divisions arrived in succession on 22, 23, 24, and 25 June 1781. Each division halted here for two extra days, the Fourth leaving only on 28 June. The artillery park (indicated here and elsewhere in pink) was ferried across the river and camped beyond Hartford while the infantry regiments were encamped in East Hartford
      MS, No. 14-5. [Rice/Brown, p. 129]
      Cf. Berthier's journal, p. 247.
    - 19. Sixième Journée. Le 25, 26, 27, 28 de d'Esthartfod à Farmington, 12 milles 1/2, undated; 1 item 23 x 34 cm (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-6)
      Sixth Day's March: from East Hartford to Farmington. 25-28 June 1781. The white square to the left of the word "Hartford" corresponds to the present site of the Old State House (built in 1796). The symbol resembling two posts (I I) on the crest of the hill, above the letter "D" of Hartford, designated the gallows on the Gallows Hill. See Itinerary 2 n. 26, where this "justice" is mentioned. "West Division" is the older term for West Hartford, which was set up as a separate town only in 1854.
      MS, No. 14-6. [Rice/Brown, pp. 129-130]
      Cf. Francois de Dainville, Le Language des Géographes (Paris, 1964), pp. 301-302, Fig. 44.
    - 20. Septième Journée. Le 26, 27, 28, 29 de Farmington à Baron's Tavern, 13 milles, undated; 1 item 23 x 28 cm (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-7)
      Seventh Day's March: from Farmington to Barne's Tavern. 26-29 June 1781. The cluster of houses designated here as "Formington. Village" is within the boundaries of the present town of Plainville (incorporated in 1869). "Soudington" is Southington. "Baron's Taverne," where the army camped, was Barnes' Tavern, in present Marion in the town of Southington, Connecticut, on what was later named French Hill. The "Chn. de meridon," beyond Barne's Tavern, is the Meriden Road.
      MS, No. 14-7. [Rice/Brown, p. 130]
    - 21. Huitième Journée. Le 27, 28, 29, 30 de Baron's Tavern à Break Neck, 13 milles, undated; 1 item 23 x 34.5 cm (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-8)
      Eighth Day's March: from Barne's Tavern to Break Neck. 27-30 June 1781. The "Nacketack" is the Naugatuck River at Waterbury. Break Neck Hill, where the army camped, is in the town of Middlebury, a high point between the watershed of the Naugatuck to the east and the Housatonic to the west. The French all seemed to agree (cf. Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, p. 30) that Break Neck was indeed a casse-cou.
      MS, No. 14-8. [Rice/Brown, p. 130]
    - 22. Neuvième Journée. Le 28, 29, 30, & 1 juillet de Break Neck à New-town, 15 milles, undated; 1 item 23 x 39 cm (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-9)
      Ninth Day's March: from Break Neck to Newtown. 28-30 June - 1 July 1781. The four divisions arrived successively at the Newtown camp on 28, 29, 30, June, and 1 July 1781. The first three each halted here an extra day, but the fourth (including the Saintonge Regiment) made no extra day's halt. From here on the army marched by brigades of two divisions each. The First Brigade (including the Bourbonnais and Deux-Ponts regiments) left Newtown during the night of 30 June-1 July; the Second Brigade (including the Soissonnais and Saintonge regiments) left on 2 July. "Woodbury" here designates, not the present town of Woodbury, which is farther north, but a part of Southbury, which was separately incorporated from Woodbury only in 1787. The "Rivière de Stratford" is now called the Housatonic; the crossing shown here is near the site of the present Shepaug Dam.
      MS, No. 14-9. [Rice/Brown, p. 130]
    - 23. Dixième Journée. Le 1 et le 2 de Newtown à Ridgébury, 15 milles, undated; 1 item 23 x 33.5 cm (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-10)
      Tenth Day's March: from Newtown to Ridgebury. 1-2 July 1781. The army was now marching by brigades. The camp was at Ridgebury, a locality or parish in the northern part of the town of Ridgefield, Connecticut. Ridgebury is some 5 miles north of the village of Ridgefield proper. The map shows the camp by brigades, with a detachment of grenadiers and chasseurs in an advanced position. "Miry Broung" is Miry Brook.
      MS, No. 14-10. [Rice/Brown, p. 130]
    - 24. Onzième Journée. Le 3 juillet de Ridgebury a Nord castel, 22 milles, undated; 1 item 23 x 51 cm (including hinged square, upper right) (Portfolio VII, Packet 14-11)